<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The right of Kings conteyning a defence of their supremacy, over all persons and in all causes, as well ecclesiasticall as civill, within their severall dominions : herewithall is proved by testimony of Holy Scripture, that Christian Kinges are to haue such dignity, and execute such office in the Christian church, as Gods kinges had exercised in the church under the lawe : which part of the mysterie of Gods will, as it hath been wickedly under poperie shut up from men, so it is in our tymes right needfull that the same be opened to all Christian nations.</title>
            <author>Procter, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10151</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20410</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1281</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22102434</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22102434</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25052</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10151)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25052)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1734:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The right of Kings conteyning a defence of their supremacy, over all persons and in all causes, as well ecclesiasticall as civill, within their severall dominions : herewithall is proved by testimony of Holy Scripture, that Christian Kinges are to haue such dignity, and execute such office in the Christian church, as Gods kinges had exercised in the church under the lawe : which part of the mysterie of Gods will, as it hath been wickedly under poperie shut up from men, so it is in our tymes right needfull that the same be opened to all Christian nations.</title>
                  <author>Procter, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>G. Thorp],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Thomas Procter.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and publisher suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴ E².</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the St. John's College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Divine rights of kings.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Church of England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25052:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25052:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE RIGHT OF KINGS, CONTEYNING A DEFENCE OF THEIR SU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, over all perſons, and in all
cauſes, aſwell eccleſiaſticall as civill, within their ſeverall Dominions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>HEREWITHALL IS PROVED BY TESTIMONY</hi> of Holy Scripture, That Chriſtian Kinges are to
haue ſuch Dignity, and execute ſuch Office in the Chriſtian Church, as Gods Kinges had and
exerciſed in the Church under the Lawe.</p>
            <p>WHICH PART OF THE MYSTERIE of Gods Will, as it hath been wickedly under Poperie ſhut up from
Men, ſo it is in our tymes right needfull that the ſame be opened to all Chriſtian
Nations.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 13.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Let every ſoule be ſubiect, to the Higher Powers.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:25052:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25052:2"/>
            <head>The epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho that conſiders the evills done unto the Sonne of God by Kings: Who that conſiders that
moſt cruel perſecution of the Church by Kings in the primitive tymes, &amp; this alſo for
about three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares of continuance: yea, who that conſiders the Churches perſecution by
Kings in theſe laſt tymes, wherein our Princes being miſs-led by the deluſions of the
Romane Biſhop, haue perſecuted them who ſuffered their faith and ſervice of God, to be
inſtructed and ordered by the word of God: who (I ſay) that conſiders theſe things, would
not expect, that the Lord, even our moſt bleſſed God, ſhould utterly reject them, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying
them any dignity or office in his Church upon earth? But the Lord of Lords, and King of Kings,
Righteous beyond our appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, and mercifull beyond all expectation, hath contrarywiſe
reveiled from heaven by his word, and witneſſed unto it with mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous power, that the Kings
among the Nations of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, are accepted by him for his Miniſters, unto whom, as unto
Kings allowed by God, all Christians muſt be ſubiect. By how much the leſſe therefore their
deſert hath been, by ſo much the more is this Grace of God to be magnified: By how much the
leſſe their deſert of this grace hath been, by ſo much the more are they bound, to attend
diligently to the due execution of the will of God. Is it not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, that Kings being
miſs-lead, partly by Heatheniſme before their converſion to Chriſtianity, partly by Poperie
after their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, haue heretofore bloudily perſecuted and ſlaine thoſe, who haue
yeilded obedience to the word of God? Shall the Saints, euen to this day alſo, be butchered by
their power? when the Lord is ſo gratious as to mainteyne the right of Kings, will not they doe
<pb facs="tcp:25052:3"/>right to the children of God? how long ſhall a falfe word miſslead the moſt of
them? how long will they be, before they by the light of the word of God diſcerne the Lords
ſheepe from others? Bleſſed be God, who hath opened the eyes of many of them, and moved their
harts to be Protectors of his flock. His Flock are thoſe, who, if not fully, yet most neerely
conforme their faith, their life and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, to the reveiled will of God, as it is
preſerved in the ſacred ſcriptures. As therefore the Lord is mercifull to Kings, ſo ought
they in duety to God, by the word of God in ſcripture to diſcerne, and diſcerning to protect
the people of the Lord. Much of the Lords people are miſs-lead by Teachers, who teach evilly in
ſome things, and hardly finde we any wholly conformable to the instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords word in
Scripture; but yet difference is to be put, betweene thoſe who in the greateſt part obey the
word of the Lord, &amp; thoſe who in the greatest part walk in diſobedience. And my hope is,
that as by this Treatiſe I move Gods people, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der adviſedly the great Dignity and
Office of Princes, ſo Princes will be gratious to thoſe, who most neerely Beleeve and live as
becommeth Saints. Neyther would I haue my Reader here to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, that I would iudge who or who are
lawfully Kings; but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that theſe who are Kinges by the permiſſion and grace of God, may
be put in minde of their Dignity and Office in the Church &amp; be alſo obeyed by thoſe of the
Church, as God by his instruction reveiled to the Church gives direction. This is the end of my
writing this following Treatiſe: this the aime of my heart; which having now ſhowen in this
epiſtle, I think fit to put an end to the ſame, and to proceed to the Treatiſe it
ſelfe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord, Thomas Proctor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:25052:3"/>
            <head>A TREATISE OF SUPREMACY.</head>
            <head type="sub">Wherein is proved by teſtimony of ſacred Scripture, that Kings or independant
civill powers or States, are by Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to be ſupreame Governours, over all perſons,
and in all cauſes, aſwell eccleſiasticall as Civill, within their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall
Dominions.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath been of long time, and in too many Nations of Chriſtendome ſtill is, an errour of
no ſmall importance to think, That Kinges are not to judge in things perteyning to the Church of
God, nor to order the offices and affaires of the Church, nor to governe over all
eccleſiaſticall perſons, within their ſeverall kingdomes or Dominions. From which errours
poſſeſſing the mindes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well of Princes as of private perſons, ſtrange troubles haue
ariſen to the church of God; both Princes and private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons miſtaking their dueties; and
ſo Princes not doing in the church what God appoints them, others, (and even of their ſubjects)
haue been ſcourges unto them, by practiſing againſt them things farre differing from the
teaching of Chriſtian Religion. Alas how much innocent blond haue Princes ſhed, whilſt guided
by a falſe word of the Romane Biſhop, they haue neglected to meditate in the word of God, and
to Iudge and Governe according to its directions, and ſo haue butchered the Saincts of God in all
Nations, and on the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary haue exalted them who moſt haue troden under foote, the ſacred
word and ordinances of the living God. What ſhould therefore be more deare to Princes, then to
know the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:25052:4"/>dignity and true office, wherein God by his Ordinance hath ſet them? Or what
greater honour can be done them, then when ſome wicked Biſhop would depreſſe their right
herein, God by his word declares his wickedneſs, and by his ſtrange and mervailous Acts in our
times, raiſeth his Princes, (will or nill that Biſhop, and all his Adherents) to their true
dignity and office in the Church? Verily we ſee in theſe times, how God tendereth the rights of
Chriſtian Princes, when under the Reformation, as he on the one hand hath freed them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
uſurpations and bondage of the Romane Biſhop, ſo on the other hand he hath preſerved their
right againſt all, who under any pretences whatſoever, haue indeavoured to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive them
thereof. It is therefore dangerous for any, aſwel for Princes as for people, to doe oughts
againſt the will of God, as he hath revealed the ſame by his word preſerved in ſcripture.
True it is, that many are not ſuffered to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed hereof, becauſe by ſuch information,
that Biſhop of Romes deluſions, and his inſufferable abuſions would be diſcovered. But
fitter it is, that Princes know their Right, and people their dueties, then that the conſciences
of both being miſsinformed, they be led thereby into the fierce wrath of God, by their doing
things contrary to his ſacred Minde. The conſideration wherof provoked me to the writing of
this Treatiſe, that ſo I alſo with others before me, may helpe to ſatiſfie the
conſciences of men, in this great point of Chriſtian Religion, concerning the Supremacy and
governement of Kings in the Church upon earth. Thus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſhowen you the Aime, Occaſion and
End of this wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, I will proceed to prove this pointe, by teſtimonyes of holy ſcripture;
that ſo, as there is no ſafer direction for men what to beleeve herein, then the directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of
Gods own word, ſo men may reſt ſatiſfied in Conſcience, with that which truely is made
manifeſt therefrom.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:25052:4"/>
            <p>In the epiſtle to the Romanes, chap. 13. verſe 1, we thus read;
<q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Let every ſoule be ſubiect to the Higher Powers: for there is no power but of God: and
the powers that be are ordeyned of God; whoſoever therefore reſisteth the power, reſiſteth
the ordinance of God: and they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves iudgement. For
Princes are not to be feared for good workes but for evill; wilt thou then be without feare of the
power? Doe well: ſo ſhalt thou haue praiſe of the ſame: for he is the Miniſter of God for
thy wealth; But if thou doe evill, feare: for he beareth not the ſword for nought: for he is the
Miniſter of God, to take vengeance on him that doth evill. Wherefore ye muſt be ſubiect, not
becauſe of wrath onely, but alſo for conſcience ſake: for for this cauſe yee pay alſo
Tribute: for they are Gods miniſters, applying themſelves for the ſame
thinge.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>In this portion of ſcripture given us, as a declaration of the will of God concerning this
matter, I wiſh you to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve;
<list>
                  <item>1. To whom the Apoſtle giveth this charge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſubjection.</item>
                  <item>2. Of what kinde of powers he here ſpeaketh.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the firſt of theſe, we ſhall doe well to obſerve, both the direction and
alſo the cloſe of this epiſtle: for by them will appeare, to whom the Apoſtle gives this
charge concerning ſubiection. The direction of the epiſtle, hath (chap. 1. verſe 7.) theſe
words: <hi>To all you that be at Rome, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of God, called to be Saincts,</hi> &amp;c. The
Cloſe of the epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, is, chap. 16.3. where wee finde a number ſaluted by name, of whom we
may well beleeve that ſome were of the Clergy: and this the rather alſo, becauſe (verſe 7.)
the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, <hi>Salute Andronicus and Iunia, my coſens, and fellow priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:25052:5"/>whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h are notable among the
Apoſtles, &amp; were in Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me;</hi> for we may well thinke, that they who were
notable among the Apoſtles, were of the Clergy, yea of the chiefe among the Clergy. Moreover,
ſeing this epiſtle was written in a tyme of good growth of the Chriſtian Church, (for it was
written after Paul had been a priſoner, ch. 16.7.) ſhould we think that the Church at Rome, was
not at this time pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided of Clergy as other Churches then planted were? To conclude, ſeing the
Apoſtle writeth to the Saints at Rome, it argues he wrote to the Church at Rome; therefore alſo
the charge concerning ſubiection, is given to All that were then in the Church at Rome. Wherefore
unleſſe we will be diſobedient to this charge of the Apoſtles: or unleſs we wil preferr
the now Biſhop and Clergy of Rome, to theſe who were notable even among the Apoſtles of the
Lord, we ought not to exempt the now Clergy of the Church of Rome, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yeilding ſubmiſſion
to the Higher powers. Thus having ſhowen to whom this charge concerning ſubjection is given,
proceed we to conſider, <hi>of what kinde of powers the Apoſtle here ſpeaketh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The kinde of power which the Apoſtle here ſpeaketh of, is noted and declared unto us by two
things: firſt, by bearing the ſword: ſecondly, By receiving tribute; but in thoſe times
Biſhops bare not the ſword, nor received Tribute, but Kings and independant Civill powers onely
did this; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the powers wherof the Apoſtle here ſpeaketh, were not Biſhops of the
Church, but Kinges, or independant Civill powers. To conclude then, ſeing the Apoſtle writing
to the Church, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands all in the ſame to be ſubject to the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Powers: and ſeing by
thoſe Higher powers he meanes thoſe who bare the ſworde, and received Tribute, that is, the
Emperour, Kings, and other Civill powers; therefore the powers eccleſiaſticall at that time at
Rome, were ſubjec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:25052:5"/>to the Emperour, and to them that bare the ſword and received Tribute, that is,
Kinges and Soveraigne Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, It is therefore the manifeſt will of God, that the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of
Chriſtian Churches, ſhould be ſubject to Kinges and Soveraigne Civill States, as to the
Higher powers by the Ordinance of God: for this Rule of the Apoſtle here ſet downe, muſt be
taken for a Rule unto all Chriſtian Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and not as ſerving for the Church of Rome onely,
and onely for that preſent tyme. If it be objected that by this Rule I ſubject the Sonne of God
alſo to Kings and Princes, I anſwere, ſeing the Lord paid tribute, <hi>Math. 17.24.</hi> and
ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Apoſtle makes the paying of Tribute, an argument of ſubjection, <hi>Rom.
13.6.</hi> therefore there was one part of our Lords Humiliation, that he was made, as inferiour to
Angels, <hi>Heb. 2.7,</hi> ſo ſubject to Kinges and Princes. Thus having writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of theſe
two things, proceede we now to conſider fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
<list>
                  <item>1. The Supremacy of Kinges.</item>
                  <item>2. Some particulars of their Office here mentioned by the Apoſtle.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Supremacy is noted unto us, by the Apoſtles ſtyling them <hi>The Higher Powers:</hi> for
they are called here Higher Powers in reſpect of the Churches powers and miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to
which the Apoſtle wrote. I conclude therefore, that ſeing the Apoſtle writing to a
Chriſtian Church, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands ſubjection to ſome as to Higher powers, therefore of the two
powers, (that of the Church, I meane, and that of Princes,) the power of Princes is the Higher by
the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God. And this is anſwerable to the Cuſtome of Scripture, which ſpeaking of
the two Powers of Kings and Prieſts, preferreth that of Kings to that of Prieſts, ſaying,
<hi>Rev. 5.10,</hi> Kinges and Prieſts, not Prieſtes and Kings; Both are powers of great
excellence; but in the matter of prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:25052:6"/>powers to powers, miniſtrations to miniſtrations, it is fit we follow the
Teaching of God, rather then the vaine word of a puffed up Biſhop. Laſtly, ſeing the
Apoſtle ſaith: <hi>let every ſoule be ſubiect to the Higher Powers,</hi> this plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
proves the Supremacy to be in thoſe powers: for ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to any as to the Higher argues
Supremacy in the Higher, though every ſubjection proves not a Supremacie in him to whom an other
is ſubjected; for even Kinges are ſubjected to be obedient to Prieſtes, when yet they obey
not them as Higher then themſelves. Thus having written of the Supremacy, proceed we to ſuch
<hi>particulars of the Kings Office</hi> as are here mentioned.</p>
            <p>The particulars here mentioned are two, firſt, <hi>That they are appointed for the wealth of
them that doe well:</hi> ſecondly, <hi>That they are to take vengeance on him that doth
evill</hi> Now then, if they be Gods Miniſters to puniſh him that doth evill, how is any evill
doer exempted from this Miniſters ſword? and if none, then no Biſhop doing evill, but is
ſubjected by God to be ſtruck by the ſworde of theſe Higher powers, as Gods Miniſters to
take vengeance on him for doing evil. Moreover, what is well doing: but the obſervation of Gods
commandement or ordinance? and what is evill doing, but the violation of the ſame? therefore in
aſmuch as this Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is to puniſh evill, his puniſhment muſt ſtretch unto evill of
all kindes, aſwell euills of the Church, as evills of the Common wealth, for the Commandements or
Ordinances of God ſtretch to both. If therefore any Teachers teach wholeſome doctrine,
according to the will of God reveiled, this is to doe well, and ſuch are to be cheriſhed and
defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by this Miniſter of the ſworde; but doe any teach falſe doctrines, contrary to the
teaching of Gods will revealed, this is to doe evill, and ſuch Teachers are to be puniſhed by
this Miniſter as evill doers. Againe, doe any eccleſiaſticall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:25052:6"/>Officers doe the duetyes ordeyned by God to their offices, this is well doing,
and ſuch Officers are to be cheriſhed and rewarded by this Miniſter; but doe any neglect the
proper duties of their Miniſtration, giving themſelves to doe other things rather, and leaving
them to be done by others, this is evill doing in ſuch Officers, and they are to be puniſhed by
this Miniſter. Laſtly, doe any Chriſtians, (of what ſort, or condition ſoever) beleeve
according to the inſtruction of Gods word; and live in their lives and converſations
accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, this is well doing, and ſuch are to be cheriſhed and defended by this Miniſter;
but doe any refuſe to Beleeve ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to wholeſome doctrine, or to live in life and
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation according to Gods Commandements, this is evill doing, and ſuch are to be
puniſhed by this Miniſter as for evill doers.</p>
            <p>Thus having briefly ſhewed the thinges moſt evident in this Scripture, I proceede to a yet
further opening of this Scripture unto you.</p>
            <p>You ſee here that Princes whoſe office properly it is, to beare the ſworde, and to receive
Tribute, are declared by the Apoſtle to be Gods Miniſters: for ſo the Apoſtle ſaith:
<hi>He is the Miniſter of God for thy wealth,</hi> and againe, <hi>He is the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of God,
to take vengeance on him that doeth evill.</hi> Now Princes bearing the ſword, and receiving
Tribute, are Kings, or independant powers or States, whom God, (not any Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, nor the Church,)
ordereth to this independancy or Soueraignety in power; for ſo the Apoſtle would haue us to
underſtand when he ſaith: <hi>there is no power but of God, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whoſoever reſiſteth
the power reſisteth the ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt, ſhall receive to
themſelves judgement.</hi> And it is the Apoſtles ſtrong argument, that becauſe Princes are
allowed of by God as for his Miniſters, therefore of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence towards God, &amp; not for
feare of wrath onely, we muſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:25052:7"/>be ſubject. Now then, ſeing God gratiouſly accepted of the Kings among the
Gentiles as for his Miniſters, what mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration is approved of in their hands by the Lord but
the Kingly? For God accepting of them as Kings, and not as private Perſons onely, he declares
himſelf hereby to approve, of their exerciſing upon earth the Kingly Miniſtration: for he
that accepts them as for Miniſters allowes in them a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, and what miniſtration
allowes he in Kings but the kingly? Therefore it is a point of Chriſtian faith neceſſary to
ſalvation, to beleeve of the Soueraigne Kinges and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which the Goſpel found among the
Gentiles, that God accepted of them as for his Kings, to ſerve him in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Miniſtration.
It was commanded to the Church under the Lawe, Deut. 17.14. that if it would ſet a King over it,
it ſhould not then take liberty to its ſelfe to ſet this or that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon over its ſelfe,
but ſhould waite upon God to ſet him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it whom the Lord ſhould chuſe; for ſo we read
there in theſe wordes: <hi>when thou ſhalt come into the land which the Lord thy God giveth
thee, and ſhalt poſſeſſe it and dwell therein, if thou ſay, I will ſet a King over
me, like as all the Nations that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout me, Then thou ſhalt make him King over thee, whom the
Lord thy God shall chuſe.</hi> It is no ſmall matter therefore to the Church of God to yeild
its ſelfe to any as for its King; for if it waite not upon Gods election, it ſurely
tranſgreſſeth grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly againſt God. Therefore the Chriſtian Church alſo, as it was
not (hand over head, at its pleaſure) to ſet Kinges over its ſelfe, ſo it was to
acknowledge and obey the Kings and Princes, already reigning over the Nations whereinto it
ſtretched, as for kinges already provided for it by the order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Ordinance of the Lord. This
approving therefore of the kinges and Princes, which the Goſpell found reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over the Nations
of the Gentiles, ſerves as Gods election or choiſe made by him, of who the Church ſhould take
and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25052:7"/>acknowledge, as for her kinges and Princes ſet Over her by Gods providence.
They then aroſe and fell, on ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting another, now the army, now the City, now the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
now the Emperors, chuſing who ſhould Rule over the Nations here and there, and yet for all
this, Gods diſpoſing hand was buſy, ordering ſuch to Soveraignety, as he would haue to
manage the power of the ſworde here and there: and the Church was ſubjected to receive and
acknowledge thoſe, whom God permitted to atteyne to Soveraignety in this Nation or in that.
Princes therefore may by diverſe Meanes attayne to Soveraignety, and the Nations may here and
there change from one to another as occaſion ſhall be given; but the Church as the Church
muſt not ſet over its ſelf a kinge or kinges, but muſt waite upon God, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging them
that attayne to the Soueraignety of power here or there. But now, Gods approving of the Kinges,
which the Goſpell found reigning over the Nations of the Gentiles, as for his Miniſters, what
followes, but that he approves in them, an exerciſing the kingly Miniſtration? And what can be
more truely the kingly Miniſtration, then that which Gods Kings before time allowed by God,
exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in the Church under the Lawe? for where there is no new deſcription of the
Miniſtration, there the ſame Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration before approved of by God in his Kinges,
ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth for an example of the kingly Miniſtration.</p>
            <p>Wherefore ſeing God accepts of Kinges as Kinges for his Miniſters, it neceſſarily
followes, that thoſe Kings exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe ſuch Miniſtration, as with Gods approbation Gods
Kinges before tyme exerciſed. I conclude therefore, that the Kings or Soueraigne States or Powers
among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, were now declared by Gods Apoſtle to haue right, to exerciſe ſuch
Miniſtration, as Gods Kinges exerciſed with Gods approbation under the Lawe. And you ſee,
that as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:25052:8"/>under the Lawe, Kings had the Supremacy, and were Gods Miniſters, <hi>for the
wealth of them that did well, and for the pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhment of evill doers,</hi> ſo the Apoſtle
calls the Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces among the Gentiles <hi>The Higher powers,</hi> and declares them for
Gods <hi>Miniſters, for the wealth of them that doe well, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of evill doers;</hi>
the likenes therefore in theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, argues Gods approving, that they ſhould be like
his former Kings in their Miniſtration. As therefore the church under the Lawe, tooke example for
her King fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Kinges of the Gentile Nations, ſo God approving of the Kinges among the
Gentiles, they are to take example for their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, from that which with Gods approbation
Kinges did in the Church under the Lawe. This I preſs the more, becauſe the Pope of Rome admits
eaſely of Kings as of hang men, to puniſh the Clergy of the Church for evill doing, when he
ſhall give up ſuch Clergy to be executed or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſworde; but at no hand will
admit, that they ſhould exerciſe ſuch Miniſtration, as Gods Kinges with Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation
exerciſed in and over the Church under the Law. This is one of his deluſions, this one of his
preſumptions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ordinances of God and of Chriſt, and by this he worketh to the
Chriſtian world, not a little miſchiefe. But now, unleſs the Chriſtian Nations will make
the Pope of Rome their Apoſtle, they ought to beleeve concerning this matter, according to the
revelation of the will of God by the Apoſtle Paul; neither ſhall they be guiltleſſe before
God, if they beleeve the Popes word, the ſame being diverſe from the word of Gods true
Apoſtle. To conclude, ſeing God approves of Kinges as Kings for his Miniſters, they are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
as they will anſwere it to God, to exerciſe ſuch kingly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, as with Gods
allowance his Kings before time ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed; for ſeing Chriſtian Religion allowes not, of all
things done by Kings among the Gentile Nations whilſt they were
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:25052:8"/>Infidells, it muſt needs be, that the Kings of the Gentiles are not to doe all
that which they as Infidels did, but ſuch things as with Gods allowance his Kings before time
did, ſo faire forth as Chriſtian Religion permits. This I add here, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the
aboliſhing of Sacrifices for ſinnes, which under the lawe were offred by Kinges: as alſo
becauſe that under Gentiliſme, Kinges were both Kinges and Preiſts, whereas Gods Ordinance
under the Chriſtianity, as under the Lawe, permits not this. But now, having proved, that God
accepts of the Kings of the Gentiles as Kings for his Miniſters: &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſhowen you, they
are to take example for the ſame fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods Kings in the Church under the Law, I think fit in the
next place to put you in minde of two ſpeciall things:
<list>
                  <item>1. That under the Lawe, the worde of God was given to the King.</item>
                  <item>2. That it was given to him as to a Iudge.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>That the worde of God was given to the King, may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the teſtimony of our bleſſed
Saviour, who <hi>(Ioh. 10.35.)</hi> ſaith: If he called them Gods, unto whom the word of God was
given, &amp;c. for, though Prieſts are compriſed under the Name of theſe Gods, yet Kinges are
not excluded, ſeing none can deny Kings to be Princes. And here I would haue you to note, that
this manner ſpeaking of our Lord, argues a kinde of truſt, as if God intruſted the keeping of
his word unto Kings and Prieſts: for when it is ſayd that the word is given to them, it implies
that God truſteth them with his word. But to this ſcripture, we may add another, <hi>Deut.
17.18.</hi> where the charge of God to the Kinge, is given in theſe wordes, ſaying: <hi>And
when he ſhall ſit upon the throne of his Kingdome, then ſhall he write him this Lawe,
repeated in a book
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:25052:9"/>by the Preists of the Levites. And it ſhalbe with him, and he ſhall reade
therein all the dayes of his life, that he may learne to feare the Lord his God, and to keepe all
the words of this Lawe, and theſe Ordinances for to doe them. That his heart be not lifted up
aboue his brethren, and that he turne not from the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to the right hand or to the
left.</hi> Here obſerve, firſt, That not what the Prieſt will deliver for Lawe, but the Lawe
its ſelfe, <hi>This Lawe</hi> he hath right, yea and charge alſo from God to take: Secondly,
that this Lawe is given to him as to a King, therefore as to to a Miniſter, and not as to a
private Perſon; therefore alſo it is not given him for his private di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection onely, what to
beleeve and doe for his owne ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but it is given him for a direction of his
Miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for what is given to an Officer as an officer, is given for a direction what to
doe in his office. Therefore Kings haue a charge of Gods word aſwell as Prieſts, and they are
to be directed by it in their Miniſtration; ſo that they may not content themſelves to ſay,
I doe this and this in my Office, by the teaching of the Prieſts, but they muſt reade and
me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate in the word its ſelfe of God, by it to be inſtructed what to doe. There is difference
to be put, betweene the Miniſter revealing primarily the word of God, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the
word already reveiled; of the firſt, the greateſt Kinges are ſubjected to receive the word as
they deliver it; but the word once ſo delivered, the King is to take it, and to reade and
meditate in it, and is not bounde to take onely the interpretation or word of him, who is but the
Miniſter of the word already reveiled. Therefore alſo the King is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſed, betweene God,
and the Miniſter of the worde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready reveiled, as having right to take the word its ſelfe
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veiled, and not whatſoever the Miniſter of the worde alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy reveiled, will deliver as for
that word. Would God that Chriſtian Princes did duely conſider, this gratious goodneſs,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:25052:9"/>and mervailous favour of God towards them; for if they duly conſidered this,
it would much provoke them to reade themſelves the revealed word of God, and not to leave this to
the reading of Prieſts onely. How will they anſwer it to God, if being Kings, as by Gods
ordination, they neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect this charge given by God to his Kings? Ah the evils which the falſe
word of an evill Prieſt hath brought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, through their neglecting themſelves to read
the word of God in Scripture. But now, as I have before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that Gods accepting of the Kings
of the Gentiles, as kings for his Miniſters, ſerves both as for Gods gracious ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction made of
them, and alſo as for a warrant, that they ſhould ſerve God in the kings miniſtration,
approved of by God in the hands of his kings under the law, ſo it may now appeare unto them, that
the charge of God given to his kings in the Church under the Law, ſerves alſo for a charge unto
them. And ſeeing this charge is given to the kinge as kinge, it proves, that his charge is, that
he ſee all the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God obſerved by all: for this uſe of this charge, made the good
kings in the Church under the law, as their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold actions, both in reſtoring true Doctrine,
and ordering the Prieſts and Levites to their ſeverall offices, as alſo in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the
divine ſervice, and other like, plentifully declare. What therefore God hath commanded or
ordayned, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for matter of faith neceſſarie to ſalvation to be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, or for matter
of Eccleſiaſticall government, or the like, that is the King to ſee done, as well by
Prieſts as People, and to puniſh the negligent for euil doers, aſwel Prieſts as others.
Thus having written of the firſt things, proceed we to the ſecond.</p>
            <p>That Gods word is given to the King, as to a Iudge, and not as to one who muſt doe after the
judgement of the Prieſt onely, may appeare <hi>Pſal. 82.1.</hi> where we thus reade:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:25052:10"/>
               <hi>He iudgeth among Gods: How long will ye iudge uniuſtly, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the
perſons of the wicked? Doe right to the poore and father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe: doe iuſtice to the poore
and needie: ſave them from the hands of the wicked.</hi> Here you ſee, that Princes of whom our
Lord teſtifies (as before I have ſhewen) that they are called Gods, are alſo Iudges;
therefore the word given to them, is given to them as Iudges. And whereby then ſhould they be
directed in their iudging, if not by the word given by God unto them? The Pope of Rome would have
them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the good, &amp; puniſh evill doers, after he and his Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy hath judged them
good or evill; but they are not to bee directed by an others judgment, ſeeing God hath made them
Iudges, and given them his word to direct their iudgement. As therefore their office ſtretcheth,
to reforme Doctrine, to order Eccleſiaſticall Officers, to ſee to their executing their
offices according to Gods ordinance, to order the Divine worſhip, and to cauſe people to live
as Gods word comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, (for all this did the good Kings in the Church under the Law) ſo they
are to Iudge alſo in all theſe things, what is to be done, what not: what well, what evilly
done. If any will ſay, that now I ſow the ſeeds of grievous tribulation to Gods Church,
ſeeing I make Kings or Princes (who are apt to maintain every conceipt of theirs by the ſword)
Iudges of Doctrine, Eccleſiaſticall offices, ordering Divine Service, and of Manners, then I
anſwer: If the Apoſtle taught this Doctrine of them, implied in his declaring that God
accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them for his miniſters, even whilſt as yet they were In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels, &amp; would not be
directed by the word of God, ſhould we deny Kings this power and office when they are
Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans? Therfore let us in theſe dayes, as the Apoſtle in thoſe, acknowledge unto
Princes their Right and Power, yea though they execute not their Miniſtery rightly, but
perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute rather the Saints and Church of God: for it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:25052:10"/>Chriſtians to acknowledge their right, yea when they doe not according to
right, but are rather enemies as yet, and perſecuters. Let us feare even then to doe evill,
becauſe if even then they puniſh us for evill, their puniſhment is Gods, ſeeing they are
the Miniſters of God. But if wee ſuffer for well doing (they being negligent to read the word,
or to judge us by it) let us take to us the comfort of the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> where <hi>1.
Pet. 2-20.</hi> he ſayth, <hi>If when ye doe well, ye ſuffer wrong, and take it patiently, this
is acceptable to God.</hi> This graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſolation againſt the afflictions layd vpon us, by
miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guided, or miſ-judging Princes, ſhould bee our refuge, as it was the refuge of Gods
Saints in thoſe times of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. Yet here I think fit to put men in minde, that wherein
Gods word preſerved doth not ſpeak for us, there, we who ſuffer, beare our owne burthen and
hurt: for wee ought to preferre the judgement of Gods Iudges before ours, though we preferre
juſtly Gods word it ſelfe to their erring in the uſe made of it. For Gods word which is
plaine, or indeed truely collected, let us ſuffer, if our Kings, erring, will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute us for
our faith, and ordering of things according thereto; but let us not ſuffer for maintenance of our
owne judgment onely, oppoſed to the iudgement of Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. True it is, that Kings and
Princes may, and in fact have erred, and this alſo in things wherein they think themſelves
free, to doe with their owne what they will; therfore Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces may doe well in ſuch things, to
admit of wholeſome counſell, rather then to goe on in doing evill through error. Some Princes
thinking themſelves free, to Honour Prieſts as they will, have in way of honour to them, left
all iudging of Doctrines of faith, and all ordering of Eccleſiaſticall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to them onely,
not daring to bee themſelves Iudges in theſe things; but ſuch honouring is not acceptable to
God, ſeeing themſelves neglect the office of Iudging, which God
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:25052:11"/>hath intruſted to them as well as to Prieſts. Others have in way of Honour
freed the Cleargie from being ſubiect to be judged and puniſhed by themſelues, unleſſe by
the Pope, or other chiefe among the Cleargie, they bee given up to the ſecular power; but this
kind of honouring alſo is evill, inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as Princes exerciſe not that power and authoritie
to judge and puniſh the Cleargie for evill doing, as Gods Kings in the Church under the Law did.
Others againe; by way of honour to Prieſts, have imployed them ſo in civill Courts of
Iuſtice, as that they have not, yea have not been able thenceforth to performe the true duties of
the Biſhops of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, but haue left the ſame to the performance of others ſubſtituted under
them; but this kinde of honouring alſo is evill, inaſmuch as Gods Miniſters of his word, who
ſhould be diligent Preachers of the ſame, content themſelves to bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie themſelves in
civill judgements, and to preach the word once in a Lent time onely, or upon ſome ſolemne time
one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Others againe, as for a greater honour to Biſhops, have made them Miniſters of the
Sword; but God having appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Kings for the miniſtration of the Sword, the other Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
muſt not be miniſters thereof: for God having put a difference between Ordinance and Ordinance,
Office and Office, Power and power, appointing one to one Miniſter, the other to another
Miniſter, what is it but a confuſion, and an inverſion of the ordinance of God, to make one
Miniſter Miniſter of both? It hath been an evill collection made by ſome, that what Gods
Prieſts under the Law did, that the Miniſters of the Goſpell may doe, even as Kings under the
Goſpell may doe what Gods Kings under the Law did: for the Ordinance of God concerning the
Miniſters under the goſpell, permits us not to make ſuch collection concerning Prieſts and
their imployment and actions. In all theſe things Princes have erred, and eaſily may againe
erre, to the great
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:25052:11"/>hurt of the Church of God, and inverſion of his holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances; therfore if
they ſuffer wholſome advice &amp; counſel in ſuch things, they ſhall the better pleaſe
God by a true mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of their office. Surely whatſoever Princes doe to Biſhops or
Prieſts, which neceſſarily occaſions their not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the proper Duties of their
Epiſcopall or Prieſtly Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, or which occaſions their over ſeldome or negligent
doing the ſame, that is ill done by Princes, and God will vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit them, both for drawing his
Miniſters of the word, from performing their proper duties of ſuch Miniſtration, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
for ſuffering unpuniſhed any ſuch omiſſion, or neglect of theſe duties. Theſe things
I thought good here to touch at, becauſe it might occaſion our Princes, to hold Gods Prieſts
to the duties proper to their Miniſtration, and to puniſh in them any omiſſion, or over
negligent performance of the ſame. But now to conclude this poynt, Princes are not bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as
executioners, to reward the good, and puniſh evill do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but they are coſtituted alſo
Iudges by the Lord, that they alſo may iudge in all things, to which the word already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed
from God, ſtretcheth. And verily, even the Miniſters of the word already revealed, are,
preaching the ſame to them, to preach as to Gods Iudges of doctrine preached. Not that they are
all alike capable of iudgement in ſuch things, but that this is the right of their office, which
alſo for conſcience towards God, muſt be had in Reverence.</p>
            <p>Thus have I proved, that Kings under the Goſpell, are to exerciſe ſuch Dignitie and
Miniſtration, as, with Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed approbation, we find in Scripture, that Gods Kings
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed under the Law. As therfore under the Law, the King was over the Church in the Nation
of the Iewes, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſayd, <hi>If thou ſay I wil ſet a King over mee,
&amp;c.</hi> (which manner Supremacie, the Kings under the Law did in fact exerciſe and hold):
And as under the Law the Kinges did not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:25052:12"/>onely reward the good, and puniſh the evill, but did alſo Iudge of good and
evill by the direction of the word given him, reſtoring pure Doctrine, and ſetting the
Prieſts and Levits to their due offices, and ordering the Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; ſo are the Kings
under the Goſpell likewiſe to doe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over the Church in their ſeverall Dominions, and
iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of what is good and evill by the word of God in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and reſtoring Religion,
ſetting the Cleargy to their due offices, and ordering the Divine Service in the Church. Wherin,
though they are not to neglect, not the advice one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but authority alſo of the Biſhops and
Prieſts, yet they are not to take for their direction, whatſoever they ſhall adviſe and
preſſe, but they ought themſelves to read and meditate in the word of God, and to judge by
it, of that adviſed and urged by the Biſhops. Theſe things concerning the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy and
Government of Kings, I have here preſſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the obſervation of Princes, partly to ſtirre
them up to mind their owne Authority in the Church, partly to inſtruct all Chriſtian Subiects,
what to beleeve concerning their dutie toward Princes; but now having this done, I think it fit to
anſwer in the next place, one or two obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which either are, or may peradventure be made,
againſt this which formerly I have written.</p>
            <div n="1" type="objection">
               <head>The first obiection.</head>
               <p>AGainſt the Supremacy of Kings, and their judging in all cauſes, and governing ouer all
perſons within their ſeverall Dominions, it commonly heretofore hath been, and to this day is
alleadged. That our Lord committed unto <hi>Peter,</hi> to be continued in his Succeſſors, the
Supreame vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riate power of governing the Church for ever. This opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they fortifie partly by
Scripture, partly by Tradition,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:25052:12"/>partly by the ſayings of Doctors of great authoritie in the Church. The
Scriptures which they commonly make uſe of, are, firſt, <hi>Math.</hi> 16.18. where the Lord
ſayd thus unto <hi>Peter, I ſay unto thee, that thou art Peter, and upon this Rock will I build
my Church: and the gates of hell ſhall not overcome it.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>Iohn</hi> 21.15.
where againe the Lord ſayd thus unto the ſame Apoſtle: <hi>Simon the ſonne of Iona, lovest
thou mee? He ſayd unto Him, Yea Lord, Thou knoweſt that I love Thee. Hee ſayd unto him, Feed
my Lambs. He ſayd unto him againe the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time, Simon the ſonne of Iona, loveſt thou
me? he ſayd unto Him, Yea Lord, thou knoweſt that I loue thee. He ſayd unto him, Feed my
Sheepe. Hee ſayd unto him the third time, Simon the ſonne of Iona, lovest thou me? Peter was
ſorie becauſe he ſayd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him the third time, loveſt thou me? and he ſayd unto him,
Lord, thou knoweſt all things, thou knowest that I love thee. Ieſus ſayd unto him, Feed my
Sheep.</hi> From both theſe Scriptures they collect, that the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould
feed all the Lords ſheep for ever, both with Doctrine and Government; therefore all the Lords
ſheep, muſt receive from this Apoſtle their Doctrine and Powers, or Offices, that ſo they
may be built upon the Rock of this Apoſtles approbation or allowance. And becauſe the Apoſtle
was to doe this for ever, therefore after his death this muſt bee done by his Succeſſors, the
Popes of Rome. Hence it is that they ſeeke the Popes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of all Doctrines, and receive
their Epiſcopall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie from him, yea Kings alſo receive kingdomes of him. But now I will
in the next place diſcover the fallacy of this collection, ſhewing that theſe Scriptures are
not ſo to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, neither do intend any ſuch matter. And I think fit to write firſt
of the latter Scripture, becauſe the falſe uſe made thereof being diſcovered, it will the
more eaſily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that they make a falſe uſe of the firſt Scripture alſo.</p>
               <p>If from the Lords words in ſaying to <hi>Peter, Feed my Lambs,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:25052:13"/>feed my ſheep,</hi> it be collected, that <hi>Peter</hi> muſt feed all
Chriſts ſheep, and this alſo both with Doctrine and Government, then it followes, that the
reſt of the Apoſtles, as well as any other, muſt be thus fed by <hi>Peter,</hi> ſeeing they
alſo are a part of the Lords ſheep; but ſeeing feeding is taken in matter of Doctrine, for
the receiving of doctrine from him, or groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon the authoritie of his approbation: and
ſeeing fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in matter of Government, is taken for a bearing rule over all Chriſts ſheep,
and that all Powers or Offices Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall and civill, are to be derived from him, or
grounded upon the authoritie of his approbation; therefore I am to prove by teſtimonies of holy
Scripture, that we are not thus to underſtand the Lord in this ſpeech of his. For matter of
Doctrine, it is well knowen, that the reſt of the Apoſtles re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived not their Doctrine from
<hi>Peter,</hi> but from the Lord Chriſt, even as <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe did; neither were
they to ground or build that upon the authoritie of <hi>Peters</hi> approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which they
received immediatly from the Lord; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I conclude, that the reſt of the Apoſtles were not
fed by <hi>Peter</hi> in matter of Doctrine. Moreover, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Galat. 1.11.</hi>
teſtifies, ſaying: <hi>I certifie you brethren, that the Goſpell which was preached of me,
was not after man, for neither received I it of man, neither was I taught it, but by the
revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Ieſus Christ.</hi> By this teſtimonie it is plaine, that the Apoſtle
<hi>Peter</hi> fed not the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> with Doctrine, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Apoſtle
<hi>Paul</hi> purpoſely provides, that none ſhould conceive him to have received his Doctrine
of Man, or by Man. And as for building upon the Apoſtle <hi>Peters</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance or approbation
of his Doctrine, it were verily ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould build or
ground himſelfe for his Doctrine, upon <hi>Peters</hi> allowance thereof, or the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of
ſuch allowance, when he received his Doctrine from the Lord himſelfe: for it were truely
abſurd to ſeeke an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:25052:13"/>allowance, and to build upon the authoritie of ſuch allowance, for that
received immediately from the Lord of the Apoſtles. So likewiſe the Churches who received the
doctrine of the Apoſtle Paule, inaſmuch as they beleeved that he received it not of Peter, but
of Chriſt, how ſought they eyther, or how built they, upon the authority of the Apoſtle
Peters approbation. There was indeed an appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, <hi>Gal. 2.7.</hi> but not a building upon
ſuch approbation, ſeing the Apoſtle had a higher warrant and authority for his doctrine.
Laſtly, ſeeing it is very apparant, <hi>Mark 3.14.</hi> that our Lord himſelf choſe the
Apoſtles, and authoriſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the Apoſtolicall Miniſtrations: &amp; ſeeing the
Apoſtle Paul, <hi>Gal. 1.1.</hi> ſayth: <hi>Paul an Apostle, not of Men, neyther by Man, but by
Ieſus Christ;</hi> therefore who received not their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration from Peter, how ſhould they
receive from him the Doctrine wherof they were Apoſtolicall Miniſters? I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude therefore,
that all the Apoſtles were not fed with do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine by Peter, &amp; conſequently that Apoſtle
was not to feed all the Lords ſheepe with matter of doctrine. And as for feeding them with
Government, by exerciſing a ſupreame Rule over them, this alſo appeares to be a falſe
collectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this Scripture, inaſmuch as we finde that our Lord expreſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forbadd unto his
Apoſtles, any one of them to rule over the reſt. For, <hi>Mark 10.42.</hi> our Lord ſayd thus
unto the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles: <hi>ye know that they which delight to beare rule among the Gentiles, have
Domination ouer them, and they that be great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>among them, exerciſe authority over them; But it
ſhall not be ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you.</hi> By which ſcripture appeareth manifeſtly, that how ever
every one of the Apoſtles, was to governe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe authority over others, yet none of them
was to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne or exerciſe Authoritie over the reſt of the company of the Apoſtles. It
muſt needes therefore be a falſe, and very pernicious interpretation or collection, to affirme,
that the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:25052:14"/>Apoſtle Peter was made Governour, to exerciſe authority over all Chriſts
ſheepe, for then he was to governe and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe authority over the reſt of the Apoſtles,
which thing the Lord expreſsly forbadd. Now, if the generality hold not in the Apoſtles, how
can it hold in all Chriſts ſheepe for ever. If Peter exerciſed not ſuch univerſall
government and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over all Chriſts Sheepe, why under the pretence of this ſpeech of the
Lords, ſhould he govern and exerciſe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over all Kings? And indeed, if a man having
alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy diverſe Sheepherds, ſay to one of them, feede my Sheep, ſhould that one Shepherd
gather hereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that now he hath the charge of All his Maſters ſheepe? Why ſhould he not
ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther underſtand this, of ſome portion of ſheepe onely, which his Maſter would ſurely
allot out to his particular charge? for he might well think with himſelf, that where many
ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds are already appointed, there all the ſheepe ſhall not be committed to one onely.
Verily, that Apoſtles excellencie, even among the very Apoſtles themſelves, was ſuch, &amp;
ſuch will be acknowledged by all good Chriſtians for ever, that it needs not to be helped with
unſound and falſe interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of, and collections from holy ſcripture. Thus having
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered the falſe uſe made of the latter of the two ſcriptures, proceede we to the
firſt ſcripture. As for the firſt ſcripture, from whence ſome would collect, that all
doctrine muſt be received from Peter, and all power or offices, or at leaſt wiſe muſt be
authoriſed by the authority of his allowance or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, that ſo they may be built upon
the Rock, which Chriſt hath given to be a Rock whereon he will build his Church, this collectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
appeares to be a falſe uſe of this ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in aſmuch as the reſt of the Apoſtles
received not their doctrine, nor Power of Apoſtleſhip from the Apoſtle Peter, but from
Chriſt himſelfe; but what they received from the Lord himſelf, it were abſurd to ſeeke to
build it upon the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:25052:14"/>Authority of Peters allowance or approbation. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Paul (as I haue
before noted) ſpeaking of the power of his Apoſtleſhip, ſaith, <hi>Paul an Apoſtle, not
of men, neyther by man, but by Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> why ſayd he this, but to teach us, that we
ought not to beleeve, that he was ſuch by vertue of the allowance or approbation of any man
whatſoever. And whilſt the Apoſtolicall power was neither received from Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nor built nor
grounded upon the Authority of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, approbation or allowance, why ſhould this be
requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of Kings and Princes? Theſe ſcriptures therefore what ever they intend, yet this
which Papiſts collect, may not be Beleeved to be the thing which they intend, for you ſee, that
that which is collected from them by Papiſts, is directly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to a moſt plaine
commandement of our Lord to his Apoſtles, and to the teſtimony of the Apoſtle Paul. Thus
having by teſtimony of ſeverall ſcriptures, confuted theſe collectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s made by ſome from
theſe ſcriptures, I think it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to oppoſe, both againſt tradition, and alſo
againſt the greateſt Fathers or Biſhops, this teſtimony of holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by which is
proved, that the reſt of the Apoſtles were not fed by the Apoſtle Peter in matter of
doctrine, and that he was not to exerciſe authority or rule over them.</p>
               <p>But if the ſcripture thus witneſs, that the Apoſtle Peter himſelf might not lawfully
claime, this ſupreme governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or rule over the reſt of the Apoſtles, nor conſequently
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all Chriſts Sheep, how much leſſe lawfully then may his Succeſſor claime this? For,
as no Apoſtle could make an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man an Apoſtle, ſo no ſucceſſor could be made an
Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle by the Apoſtle Peter; and not being ſo much as an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, how ſhould he claime
the chiefeſt ſingularity of the Apoſtle Peter? And that no Apoſtle could make an
Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, I gather from the Apoſtle Paul, who <hi>(Gal. 1.1.)</hi> ſaith: <hi>Paul an
Apoſtle, not of Men, neyther by Man, but by Ieſus
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:25052:15"/>Chriſt;</hi> for this argues, that an Apoſtle, ſhould not be of Men,
neyther by Man, but by Ieſus Chriſt. I conclude therefrom, that no Succeſſor could be in
all things like the Apoſtle to whom he ſucceedeth, and much leſs then in thoſe things by
which (if by any thing) the Apoſtle Peter was preferred unto the reſt of the Apoſtles. If the
ſucceſſor haue conferred upon him, all the guifts and prerogatives of an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, what is
he then but an Apoſtle? But ſuch gifts and prerogatives as by which Apoſtles, were
Apoſtles, could not be giuen by men, but by Chriſt onely; therefore the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Peter
neyther might nor could conferre upon his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor all the power, office, prerogatives or
dignitie, which himſelf as an Apoſtle had received of the Lord Chriſt. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, ſeeing
the Lords Apoſtles were the Lords governours, ſet over the reſt of the eccleſiaſticall
Governours of the Church, how unfit were it to conceive, that the Succeſſour onely of an
Apoſtle, ſhould be Governour over any Apoſtle? But ſome are of opinion, that the Apoſtle
Iohn remained long after the death of the Apoſtle Peter; if therfore the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor of
Peter, haue a Vicariate power to governe and rule over all Chriſts Sheepe, then muſt he be this
to the Apoſtle Iohn; but what manner unſufferable ambition this favours of, I leave to the
judgement of all men. Let us therefore ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beleeve that if the Apoſtle Peter, appointed his
ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour, then yet he conferred not upon him, neyther all the guifts by which himſelf
was an Apoſtle, nor all the power Miniſteriall, nor dignity, which as being an Apoſtle, and
one of the chiefe among the Apoſtles, he held and injoyed in the Church of Chriſt; but onely,
(as Paul upon Timothie and Titus) he conferred a portion of power and charge, ſuch as a
Succeſſour might be capable of. To conclude, ſeeing no Apoſtle could conferr upon an other
man, all the guifts, offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and dignity, which himſelf injoyed as an Apoſtle, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:25052:15"/>the ſucceſſor muſt be a Miniſter of a farr inferiour rank, dignity,
and charge of Government in the Church, then was the Apoſtle Peter himſelfe. Now then, why
ſhould not ſuch a Miniſter, though he be ſucceſſour to that Apoſtle, ſubject
himſelf to the ſupreame goverment of Gods Kinges, ſo witneſſed unto by holy ſcripture
as before I have ſhowen? Thus having anſwered this objection, let us proceed to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="objection">
               <head>The ſecond Obiection.</head>
               <p>SOme peradventure may obiect, ſaying: The Kingdome of heaven comming in among the Gentiles by
Apoſtles and Biſhops, it were a ſubiecting the Kingdome of Heaven to the powers of this
world, if we maintayn not the ſupreme Government to remaine in Biſhops, and ſpecially in the
A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle Peters ſucceſſour. If any ſhould thus object, then I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: the kingdome of
heaven comprehending all power, (as the Lord ſayd, <hi>Math. 28.18. All power is given me in
heaven, and in earth</hi>) the power Apoſtolicall and Epiſcopall, muſt not be taken for the
Kingdome of heaven, as if the kingdom of heaven had in it none other powers then it. But you ſee
that I haue ſhowen before, that there are the powers of Kings in the earth, which it pleaſed
God to allow and confirm, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting gratiouſly alſo of them as for his Miniſters. Now,
though in God the fountaine of power, all power is alike as water in a fountaine, yet in
diſtributing of that Power into Miniſteriall Streames, the Lord may ordeyne which parte to
which ſhalbe ſubordinate; therefore ſeeing afore I haue ſhowen, that the Apoſtle Paul
calls the Miniſters of the ſword The Higher Powers: and ſeeing I haue before proved, that
theſe powers are allowed by God as for his Miniſters, and conſequently are to exerciſe
ſuch dignity and office in the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:25052:16"/>Church, as Gods Kings exerciſed in the Church under the Lawe: And laſtly,
ſeeing all the ſcripture ſhewes, that thoſe Kings were over all the Church, exerciſing a
ſupreame go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment over all eccleſiaſticall perſons; therefore (I ſay) it is no
ſubjecting of the kingdome of heaven to the powers of this world, to ſubject the Biſhops of
the Church, to Gods Kings and Soveraigne States. Biſhops are Miniſters of the kingdome of
heaven, but they are not all the Miniſters ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, for Kinges alſo are declared by the
Goſpell to be Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the ſame, ſeeing God hath declared himſelf to accept of them
as for his Miniſters; therefore, to ſubiect one kinde of officer of a kingdome to an other
officer, is not to ſubiect the kingdome to an other kingdome. Biſhops preach the word to
theſe to ſubdue them to Chriſt; but being ſubdued by the word miniſtred, Biſhops may
not ſay, <hi>The kingdomes of this world are ours, and we will diſpoſe of them;</hi> but they
muſt ſay, as Rev. 11.15. <hi>The kingdomes of this world are our Lordes and his Christs, and he
ſhall reigne for evermore.</hi> True it is that even the greateſt Kinges are comprehended in
that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, <hi>Heb. 13.17.</hi> where it is ſayd: <hi>Obey them that haue the
Overſight of you, and ſubmit your ſelves, for they watch for your ſoules, as they that must
give accompts, that they may doe it with ioy, not with griefe: for that is unprofitable for
you.</hi> Therefore even the greateſt Princes are ſubiected by Chriſtian religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> unto
ſpirituall Paſtors, in the things wherof they are Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; but this may be, without
Biſhops having the Supreme government. For, as a Lord of greateſt authority in a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
muſt obey to every the meaneſt Conſtable of a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, within his precinct of charge, &amp;
in that wherein ſuch Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtable is indued with power &amp; authority from the King, when yet
this makes not ſuch Lord to loſe his ſuperiority, which in the kingdome he hath over ſuch
Conſtable; ſo is it between a King and a Biſhop. God hath declared the Kings
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:25052:16"/>of the Gentiles for his Miniſters, therefore as Kinges were to Prieſtes
under the Lawe, ſo muſt they be to Biſhops un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpell: and on the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, as
Prieſts were to Kings under the Lawe, ſo may Biſhops be to Kings under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. The
King under the Lawe left the Prieſtly power and miniſtration to the Prieſt, &amp; was
obedient in all things, when yet he ceaſed not hereby to be governour over the Prieſts; even
ſo are Kinges to doe under the Goſpell. The King that muſt ſubmit himſelf, to heare the
Goſpell preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Biſhop, to receive of his hand Gods Sacraments, to uſe him as Gods
Prieſt to pray for him, and other like, yet is ſuch a Miniſter for God over ſuch Prieſt,
as that ſuch Prieſt preaching falſe doctrine, or miniſtring the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments otherwiſe
then according to Gods inſtitution, or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing otherwiſe then as Gods word in
ſcripture pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes, in ſtead of obeying ſuch Prieſt, he is over him to take vengeance
on him in Gods ſtead as for an evill doer. So likewiſe the King that doing evill, is
ſubiected to the Prieſts proceeding againſt evill doers, whether it be to diſcipline of
humiliation or ſhaming, to ſequeſtration, or excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, is yet ſuch a Miniſter for
God over the Prieſt, that the Prieſt doing this upon uniuſt cauſe, or preſſing
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt ends or effects of ſuch diſcipline, the King in ſtead of obeying, muſt puniſh
ſuch Prieſt as for an evill doer. The Pope is one of theſe wicked Prieſts, for even for
obedience to the true word of God, and for ordering things according to its direction, he uſeth
the ſword of the Church againſt men, yea againſt Kings: and not onely ſo, but having
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated any, he teacheth, that ſubiects ſhould not acknowledge nor obey their
excommunicate Kings, childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their excommunicate Parents, nor wives their excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate husbands,
and the like; but with what peace of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhall a man break Gods word, to doe according
to this
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:25052:17"/>word of the Popes? Excommunication indeed changeth condition in the
Excommunicate, but not in this meaſure, nor to this effect, for then we muſt not doe as the
ſcripture commands, in obeying the King, Honouring our parents, and yeelding one to another due
benevolence. And truly of all the wicked Prieſts that ever were in the Church, the Pope of Rome
is the wickedeſt, changing Gods Ordinance, and the effects of Eccleſiaſticall Diſcipline
ſo, that it is a wonder that he is ſuffred; ſure I am, Gods Kings ſhall anſwer for it to
God, if they as Gods Miniſters take not vengeance for God upon him for this. Thus having
anſwered this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection alſo, I will now conclude this Treatiſe with an exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to
ſubjects.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="exhortation">
               <head>An Exhortation to Subiests.</head>
               <p>SEeing God reveiling his will by his Apoſtle, declares him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to accept gratiouſly of
the Kings and Princes already among the Gentiles, as Kings and Princes already provided for the
Church among the Gentiles, and confirmed as or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined by him: And ſeeing Kings, being ſo
accepted of &amp; confirmed, are to take example for their regall dignity and Government, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
approved of dignity and government, of Gods Kings in the Church under the Lawe; therefore it
behoveth all men to yeild them due ſubjection, obeying the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> willingly as Gods Miniſters, in all
things wherein wee finde Gods Kings under the Lawe obeyed with the Lords appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation. As under the
Lawe therefore, Kings were over the Prieſts, exerciſing Authority over them, both in ſetting
them to their due Offices if they neglected them: and alſo in puniſhing them for evill doing,
1. Chron. 2.26. ſo if Kings in the Chriſtian Church doe likewiſe, Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people ought to
acknowledge, that the King is by Gods ordinance thus
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:25052:17"/>to doe. Againe, if Chriſtian Kings take care of doctrine alſo, ſeeing to
it that Biſhops and Teachers teach according to Gods word: or if they order the divine ſervice,
according to the wil of God reveiled in his word: and in a word, if they ſee the Ordinance of God
obſerved, aſwell in eccleſiaſticall as civill affaires, puniſhing alſo aſwell the
Cleargy as others of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, we ought to acknowledge, that the King is by Gods ordinance ſuch a
Miniſter, as hath right to uſe this Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Church of God within his owne
dominions. Let not men being led away of that Romiſh deluſion, by which Kings are debarred from
exerciſing in the Church, the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity &amp; Office of Gods Kings in the Church under the Law,
diſobey their Princes in their uſing their authority in theſe things, ſeing in all theſe
things the Scriptures witneſs, that Gods Kings under the Law exerciſed their authority; but
rather let men with comfort of conſcience, acknowledge this Supreame dignity and office in Kings,
that ſo they be not found reſiſters of the Ordinance of God. If any ſay, ſhould we not
make conſcience of things as our Teachers teach us? then I anſwer: That if you by evill
Teachers be led to doe evill, in diſobeying the lawfull things done by your Kings, it will not
ſerve for defence of the evill to ſay, your Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers taught you ſo; for, by what meanes
ſoever you doe evil, the King is Gods Miniſter to puniſh you for evill doing. You muſt
beware therefore of falſe Teachers, that you be not lead by them as their Diſciples into
errour, <hi>Act. 20.30:</hi> And you haue a charge giuen you by the Apoſtle, <hi>2 Theſ.
2.</hi> 15, <hi>that you be not moved by any from that which in Scripture is received from the
Apostles.</hi> Remember how the Apoſtle Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>1 Pet. 4.15.</hi> exhorts you, ſaying:
<hi>Let none of you ſuffer as an evill doer.</hi> But, are you not evill doers, if you deny your
Kings ſuch Dignity and Office, as God by his word hath conferred upon them? If therefore your
King ſee to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:25052:18"/>of Religion, according to the inſtruction of Gods word: and ſee the word to
be purely preached and the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments rightly adminiſtred unto you, are not you evill doers,
and reſiſters of Gods Ordinance, if you will not come to the word ſo adminiſtred, nor
partake of the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordered? What would you thinke of thoſe in Iudah and
Iſraell, who when Hezekiah or Ioſiah, or Iehoſhaphat, reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red pure religion, by the
inſtruction of the Lawe preſerved in ſcripture: or tooke away offenſive things: or ordered
the Preiſts and Levites to their due miniſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or the like, would not then be obedient in
ſuch Reformation? were they note<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill doers think you? were they not worthy to be puniſhed by
the King for evill doers? As you therefore would not fall into the like error, and danger, ſo
ought you to obey unto the Reformation of doctrine and of the Church, confirmed by Gods Miniſter
the King, ſo long as by the word of God, you cannot prove any thing taught, or done, to be
againſt the reveiled will of God. Think not to plead your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſeeing that your
conſcience ought to admit of Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; and there hath now long time of information
paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, wherein you ought to haue beene inſtructed by the Truth. Neither thinke, that the
ſword muſt of duty ſtay, till the worde haue prevailed to convert you: for the Miniſter of
the ſword muſt puniſh you for evill doing, and is not bound (ſave in ſhewing mercy for a
tyme) to ſtay his hand, till you obey the word, and convert from your errour. One Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
cannot warrant you againſt an other, the Prieſt againſt the King, nor the King againſt the
Prieſt, becauſe God hath ſubiected you to obey unto both of theſe; therefore nothing but
the true word of God its ſelfe, will ſerve to be alleaged for your diſobeying of eyther. If
therefore you neglect your ſelfe to reade, or heare read unto you the worde of God in
ſcripture, by which Meanes alſo you might come to know it:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:25052:18"/>Or, if you, when your Biſhop or Prieſt, declares plainely the word of God
out of the Scripture unto you, you then will follow an other Prieſt, who ſhewes you not plainly
the word of God for that which hee teacheth you, ſo following his word, be it right or wrong, not
caring to know the worde of God, then goe you a wrong courſe, and as neglecters of the word of
God, are ready for that judgement, 2 Theſ. 2.10, of being <hi>giuen up to a ſtrong deluſion,
that you ſhould beleeve lies.</hi> And truly, a very ſtrong deluſion hath the Popes
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Supreame Vicarſhip been, leading thouſands into errour, and producing in ſome very
pernicious effects. But now, ſeeing I haue ſhowen you by the word of God, that ſuch Generall
and Supreame Vicarſhip, is contrary to the expreſs teaching of the word of God in holy
Scripture, make conſcience henceforth, to hearken to the word of God, and to be guided by it in
your faith, that ſo, obeying the Truth, you may be ſaved with the children of Truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
